Today I want to talk to you about
ابتغي ان احدثكم اليوم عن
swimming across the North Pole,
السباحة عبر القطب الشمالي,
across the most northern place in the whole world.
عبر اكثر البقاع شمالية في العالم كله.
And perhaps the best place to start is with my late father.
و ربما المكان الافضل للبدء به هو المرحوم ابي.
He was a great storyteller.
كان حكاواتيا عظيما.
He could tell a story about an event,
كان يستطيع ان يروي حكاية عن حدث،
and so you felt you were absolutely there at the moment.
ولذلك تشعر انك حتما كنت هناك في تلك اللحظة.
And one of the stories he told me so often when I was a young boy
و من القصص اللتي حكاها لي مرارا عندما كنت ولدا صغيرا
was of the first British atomic bomb test.
هي عن اول اختبار بريطاني للقنبلة الذرية.
He had been there and watched it go off.
كان هناك و شاهدها تنفجر.
And he said that the explosion was so loud
و قال ان الانفجار كان مدويا
and the light was so intense,
و الضوء كان كثيفا جدا،
that he actually had to put his hands in front of his face to protect his eyes.
حتى انه كان عليه في الواقع وضع يديه امام وجه لحماية عينيه.
And he said that he could actually see an x-ray
و قال انه كان بمقدروه رؤية اشعة اكس
of his fingers,
لاصابعه
because the light was so bright.
لان الضوء كان جد مشع.
And I know that watching that atomic bomb going off
و انا اعلم ان مشاهدة انفجار القنبلة الذرية
had a very, very big impact on my late father.
كان له وقع جد كبير على المرحوم ابي.
Every holiday I had as a young boy
كل عطلة قضيتها عندما كنت ولدا صغيرا
was in a national park.
كانت في المنتزه الوطني.
What he was trying to do with me was to inspire me
ما كان يحاول فعله لي هو الهامي
to protect the world,
لحماية العالم،
and show me just how fragile the world is.
و ليريني كم هذا العالم هو هش.
He also told me about the great explorers.
و حدثني ايضا عن المستكشفين العظام.
He loved history. He would tell me about Captain Scott
كان يحب التاريخ. كان يحدثني عن القبطان سكوت
walking all the way to the South Pole
اللذي مشى كل الطريق نحو القطب الجنوبي.
and Sir Edmund Hillary climbing up Mount Everest.
و السيد ايدمند هيلاري متسلق جبل افريست.
And so ever since I think I was just six years old,
و منذ ذلك الوقت اعتقد انذاك كنت فقط ست سنوات
I dreamed of going to the polar regions.
حلمت بالذهاب الى الاماكن القطبية.
I really, really wanted to go to the Arctic.
كنت بحق اريد الذهاب الى القطب.
There was something about that place
كان هناك شيء في ذا المكان
which drew me to it.
قد اجتذبني اليه.
And, well, sometimes it takes a long time
و حسنا يتطلب وقت طويل
for a dream to come true.
للحلم ان يصبح حقيقة.
But seven years ago, I went to the Arctic
ولكن في السبع السنين الفارطة ذهبت الى القطب
for the first time.
للمرة الاولى.
And it was so beautiful that I've been back there
و كان من الجميل العودة الى هناك
ever since, for the last seven years.
و منذ ذاك في السنوات السبع الاخيرة.
I love the place.
احب المكان.
But I have seen that place change
ولكني رايت تغير ذاك المكان
beyond all description,
فوق كل التصورات،
just in that short period of time.
في تلك الفترة الزمنية القصيرة فقط.
I have seen polar bears walking across very, very thin ice
رايت دببة قطبية تمشي عبر جليد رقيق جدا جدا
in search of food.
بحثا عن الطعام.
I have swum in front of glaciers
لقد سبحت امام كتل جليدية
which have retreated so much.
قد تقلصت كثيرا.
And I have also, every year,
كما اني كل سنة،
seen less and less sea ice.
كنت ارى القليل فالقليل من البحر المتجمد.
And I wanted the world to know what was happening up there.
و اردت ان يعلم العالم ما يدور هناك.
In the two years before my swim,
خلال العامين الماضين قبل سباحتي،
23 percent of the arctic sea ice cover
ثلاث و عشرون بالمائة من الغطاء الجليدي للبحر بالقطب
just melted away.
ذابت.
And I wanted to really shake the lapels of world leaders
و اريد بحق ان اتشبث بثياب قادة العالم
to get them to understand what is happening.
لافهامهم ما هو جار.
So I decided to do this symbolic swim
لهذا قررت ان اقوم بهذه السباحة الرمزية
at the top of the world, in a place which should be frozen over,
على راس العالم في مكان متجمد،
but which now is rapidly unfreezing.
و هو الان يذوب بسرعة.
And the message was very clear:
و كانت الرسالة واضحة جدا:
Climate change is for real,
التغير المناخي هو حقيقي
and we need to do something about it.
علينا القيام بشيء ازاءه.
And we need to do something about it right now.
و علينا القيام بشيء بخصوصه فورا.
Well, swimming across the North Pole,
حسنا السباحة عبر القطب الشمالي،
it's not an ordinary thing to do.
هو ليس بالشيء المالوف للقيام به.
I mean, just to put it in perspective,
اريد فقط ان اضعه في اطار،
27 degrees is the temperature of a normal indoor swimming pool.
درجة حرارة مسبح عادي هي سبع و عشرون درجة.
This morning, the temperature of the English Channel was 18 degrees.
هذا الصباح كاننت حرارة القناة الانقليزية ثمانية عشرة درجة.
The passengers who fell off the Titanic
المسافرين اللذين سقطوا عن ظهر التايتانك
fell into water of just five degrees centigrade.
سقطوا في ماء بحرارة خمس درجات.
Fresh water freezes at zero.
الماء العذب يتجمد عند الصفر.
And the water at the North Pole is minus 1.7.
و الماء في الشمال القطبي هو 1.7 درجة تحت الصفر.
It's fucking freezing.
تبا انه متجمد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'm sorry, but there is no other way to describe it.
انا اسف ولكن ما من طريقة اخرى لوصف ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so I had to assemble an incredible team around me
و لذلك كان علي تجميع فريق رائع من حولي
to help me with this task.
ليساعدني في هذا العمل.
I assembled this team of 29 people from 10 nations.
جمعت هذا الفريق المتكون من تسعة و عشرون فردا من عشر بلدان.
Some people think that swimming is a very solo sport,
بعض الناس يعتقدون ان السباحة رياضة فردية،
you just dive into the sea and off you go.
انت فقط تغطس في البحر.
It couldn't be further from the truth for me.
لم تكن ابعد من الحقيقة بالنسبة لي.
And I then went and did a huge amount of training,
و من ثم ذهبت و قمت بكم هائل من التدريب.
swimming in icy water, backwards and forwards.
السباحة في ماء متجمد ذهابا و ايابا.
But the most important thing was to train my mind
و لكن الشيء الاكثر اهمية كان تدريب عقلي
to prepare myself for what was going to happen.
لاجهز نفسي لما سوف يحدث.
And I had to visualize the swim.
و كان علي ان اتخيل السباحة.
I had to see it from the beginning all the way to the end.
كان علي ان اراها من بداية الطريق الى اخره.
I had to taste the salt water in my mouth.
كان علي ان اتذوق الماء المالح في فمي.
I had to see my coach screaming for me,
كان علي ان اشاهد مدربي و هو يصرخ في،
"Come on Lewis! Come on! Go! Go! Go! Don't slow down!"
هيا لويس هيا استمر استمر استمر ولا تبطئ!
And so I literally swam across the North Pole
و اذن حرفيا سبحت عبر القطب الشمالي
hundreds and hundreds of times in my mind.
مئات و مئات المرات في عقلي.
And then, after a year of training, I felt ready.
و بعد سنة من التمرين شعرت باني مستعد.
I felt confident that I could actually
شعرت بالثقة اني استطيع بالفعل
do this swim.
القيام بالسباحة.
So myself and the five members of the team,
لهذا انا نفسي و الاعضاء الخمسة من فريقي،
we hitched a ride on an icebreaker
استقلينا كاسحة جليد
which was going to the North Pole.
كانت ذاهبة الى القطب الشمالي.
And on day four, we decided to just do a quick
و في يوم من الايام قررنا نحن الاربعة ان نقوم بـ
five minute test swim.
اختبار سريع للسباحة لخمس ثوان.
I had never swum in water of minus 1.7 degrees before,
لم اسبح قط في ماء بدرجة 1.7 تحت الصفر من قبل
because it's just impossible to train
لانه كان من المستحيل التدرب
in those types of conditions.
في هذه الاشكال من الظروف.
So we stopped the ship, as you do.
اذن اوقفنا القارب كما تفعل.
We all got down onto the ice,
و نزلنا على الجليد،
and I then got into my swimming costume
و من ثم ارتديت سترة السباحة الخاصة بي،
and I dived into the sea.
و غطست في البحر.
I have never in my life felt anything
لم اشعر في حياتي ابدا بشيء
like that moment.
كما في تلك اللحظة.
I could barely breathe. I was gasping for air.
كنت بالكاد استطيع ان اتنفس.
I was hyperventilating so much,
كنت الهث بشدة
and within seconds my hands were numb.
و خلال دقائق كانت يداي مخدرتان.
And it was -- the paradox is
و المفارقة انه
that you're in freezing cold water,
انك في ماء بارد متجمد،
but actually you're on fire.
و لكنك في الواقع تحترق.
I swam as hard as I could for five minutes.
سبحت قدر المستطاع لعشر ثوان.
I remember just trying to get out of the water.
اتذكر اني كنت فقط احاول الخروج من الماء.
I climbed out of the ice.
صعدت فوق الجليد.
And I remember taking the goggles off my face
و اتذكر اني خلعت نظارتي عن وجهي
and looking down at my hands in sheer shock,
متمعنا في اصابعي في دهشة
because my fingers
لان اصابعي
had swollen so much that they were like sausages.
قد انتفخت كثيرا حتى بدت كالنقانق.
And they were swollen so much, I couldn't even close them.
و كانت منتفخة جدا حتى انه لم يكن بمقدوري اغلاقها.
What had happened is that we are made partially of water,
و ما حدث هو اننا جزئيا مصنوعين من الماء،
and when water freezes it expands.
و عندما يتجمد الماء يتمدد.
And so what had actually happened is
و اذن ما حدث في الواقع هو
that the cells in my fingers had frozen and expanded.
ان الخلايا في اصابعي قد تجمدت و توسعت.
And they had burst. And I was in so much agony.
و تفجرت و كنت في حالة يرثى لها.
I immediately got rushed onto the ship and into a hot shower.
و صعدت في الحال الى المركب و من ثم الى حمام ساخن.
And I remember standing underneath the hot shower
و اتذكر اني كنت واقفا تحت الماء الساخن
and trying to defrost my fingers.
و احاول اذابة اصابعي.
And I thought, in two days' time, I was going to do this swim across the North Pole.
و فكرت انه في غضون يومين سوف اقوم بهذه السباحة عبر القطب الشمالي.
I was going to try and do a 20-minute swim,
كنت ساحاول و اقوم بالسباحة لمدة عشرين دقيقة،
for one kilometer across the North Pole.
لكيلومتر واحد عبر القطب الشمالي.
And this dream which I had had ever since I was a young boy
و هذا الحلم اللذي كان لدي مذ كنت طفلا صغيرا،
with my father, was just going out the window.
مع ابي كان للتو خارج النافذة،
There is no possibility that this was going to happen.
ليس هنالك احتمال ان ذلك يمكن ان يحدث.
And I remember then getting out of the shower
و اتذكر من بعد ذلك الخروج من الحمام
and realizing I couldn't even feel my hands.
مدركا اني لااستطيع حتى الشعور بيدي.
And for a swimmer, you need to feel your hands
و بالنسبة لسباح عليك ان تشعر بيديك
because you need to be able to grab the water
ليكون بمقدورك التمسك بالماء
and pull it through with you.
و السحب خلاله.
The next morning, I woke up
واستيقظت في الصباح التالي
and I was in such a state of depression,
و كنت في حالة اكتئاب.
and all I could think about was Sir Ranulph Fiennes.
و كل ما كنت استطيع التفكير فيه هو السيد رانلف فينيز.
For those of you who don't know him, he's the great British explorer.
للذين منكم لايعرفونه هو مكتشف بريطاني عظيم.
A number of years ago, he tried to ski all the way to the North Pole.
قبل عدد من السنين الماضية حاول ان يتزلج كل الطريق الى القطب الشمالي.
He accidentally fell through the ice into the sea.
سقط عن الجليد الى البحر.
And after just three minutes in that water,
و بعد ثلاث دقائق فقط في ذلك الماء،
to get himself out.
كان بمقدوره اخراج نفسه من الماء.
And his hands were so badly frostbitten
و كانت يداه قد لسعها البرد بشكل سيء
that he had to return to England.
فتحتم عليه العودة الى انجلترا.
He went to a local hospital and there they said,
ذهب الى مستشفى محلي و هناك قالوا،
"Ran, there is no possibility
"ران ليس هناك اي فرصة
of us being able to save these fingers.
لنا لكي نستطيع انقاد هذه الاصابع.
We are going to actually have to take them off."
سيتوجب علينا ان نقتلعها."
And Ran decided to go into his tool shed
وقرر ران الذهاب ورشته حيث يحتفظ بعدة النجارة
and take out a saw
و اخذ منشارا
and do it himself.
و قام بذلك بنفسه.
And all I could think of was, if that happened to Ran after three minutes,
و كل ما كان علي التفكير فبه هو ان حدث ذلك لراين بعد ثلاث دقائق،
and I can't feel my hands after five minutes,
و انا استطيع ان اشعر بيدي ابان خمس دقائق،
what on earth is going to happen if I try 20 minutes?
ماذا بحق السماء سوف يحدث اذا ما حاولت لعشرين دقيقة؟
At the very best, I'm going to end up losing some fingers.
وفي افضل الحالات سوف افقد بعض الاصابع.
And at worst, I didn't even want to think about it.
و في اسوئها لااريد حتى التفكير بذلك.
We carried on sailing through the ice packs towards the North Pole.
وواصلنا الابحار عبر الكتل الجليدية باتجاه القطب الشمالي.
And my close friend David, he saw the way I was thinking,
ولقد فهم صديقي المقرب دايفد طريقة تفكيري.
and he came up to me and he said, "Lewis,
و جاء الي و قال "لويس،
I've known you since you were 18 years old.
اعرفك منذ كنت ثمانية عشر سنة.
I've known you, and I know, Lewis,
انا اعرفك و اعرف لويس،
deep down, right deep down here,
في الصميم هنا في الصميم،
that you are going to make this swim.
انك سوف تقوم بهذه السباحة.
I so believe in you Lewis. I've seen the way you've been training.
و انا اؤمن بك لويس لقد رايت الطريقة التي كنت تتدرب بها.
And I realize the reason why you're going to do this.
وادركت الهدف اللذي من اجله سوف تفعل ذلك.
This is such an important swim.
انها سباحة مهمة.
We stand at a very, very important moment in this history,
نقف عند لحظة تاريخية مهمة.
and you're going to make a symbolic swim here
وانت سوف تقوم بسباحة رمزية
to try to shake the lapels of world leaders.
لتهز قادة العالم.
Lewis, have the courage to go in there,
لويس ليكن لديك الشجاعة للقيام بذلك
because we are going to look after you every moment of it."
لاننا سوف نعتني بك خلال كل لحظة."
And I just, I got so much confidence from him saying that,
واستمديت الثقة من كلامه ذاك،
because he knew me so well.
لانه كان يعرفني جيدا.
So we carried on sailing and we arrived at the North Pole.
وواصلنا الابحار ووصلنا الى القطب الشمالي.
And we stopped the ship,
و اوقفنا القارب،
and it was just as the scientists had predicted.
و بالضبط كما تنبا العلماء.
There were open patches of sea everywhere.
كان هناك رقع مفتوحة من البحر في كل مكان.
And I went down into my cabin
و نزلت الى قمرتي
and I put on my swimming costume.
و ارتديت سترة السباحة الخاصة بي.
And then the doctor strapped on a chest monitor,
و من ثم اخرج الطبيب عدة رسم قلب
which measures my core body temperature
لقيس درجة حرارة جسدي
and my heart rate.
ودقات قلبي.
And then we walked out onto the ice.
و من ثم مشينا فوق الجليد.
And I remember looking into the ice,
و اتذكر النظر الى الجليد
and there were big chunks of white ice in there,
و كان هناك قطع كبيرة من الجليد الابيض،
and the water was completely black.
و كان الماء كله اسود.
I had never seen black water before.
لم ار ابدا من قبل ماءا اسودا.
And it is 4,200 meters deep.
و كان عمقه يصل الى 4,200 مترا.
And I said to myself, "Lewis, don't look left, don't look right.
و قلت لنفسي "لويس لا تنظر الى يسارك لاتنظر الى يمينك.
Just scuttle forward and go for it."
امضي قدما و تقدم اليه."
And so I now want to show you a short video
و اذن اريد ان اريكم فيديو قصير
of what happened there on the ice.
عما حدث هناك على الجليد.
Narrator (Video): We're just sailing out of harbor now, and it's at this stage
فيديو: للتو نبحر بعيدا عن المرفاء وفي هذه المرحلة
when one can have a bit of a wobble mentally.
عندما يمكن للمرء أن يكون نوعا من التمايل العقلي.
Everything just looks so gray around here,
كل شيء بالجوار هنا يبدو رماديا،
and looks so cold.
و يبدو باردا جدا.
We've just seen our first polar bears.
و للتو راينا اول دببة قطبية.
It was absolutely magical.
كانت ساحرة.
A mother and a cub, such a beautiful sight.
ام و ديسم ياله من مشهد جميل.
And to think that in 30, 40 years
و افكر انه خلال ثلاثين او اربعين سنة
they could become extinct.
يكونان قد انقرضا.
It's a very frightening, very, very frightening thought.
انه مخيف جدا انها فكرة مخيفة جدا.
We're finally at the North Pole. This is
و اخيرا نحن في القطب الشمالي. هذه
months and months and months of dreaming to get here,
اشهر و اشهر و اشهر من الحلم بالوصول هناك.
years of training and planning and preparation.
سنوات من التدريب و التخطيط و التحضير.
Ooh. In a couple of hours' time I'm going to get in here and do my swim.
اه في ساعتان من الزمن سوف اكون هنا و اقوم بسباحتي.
It's all a little bit frightening,
انه مخيف قليلا،
and emotional.
و عاطقي.
Amundson, you ready? Amudson: Ready.
هل انت جاهز امندسن؟
Lewis Pugh: Ten seconds to swim. Ten seconds to swim.
عشر ثوان للسباحة عشر ثوان للسباحة.
Take the goggles off. Take the goggles off!
اخلع النظارة اخلع النظارة!
Man: Take the shoes. Take the shoes.
رجل: خذ الاحذية. خذ الاحذية.
Well done lad! You did it! You did it Lewis!
احسنت عملا يا رجل لقد فعلتها لقد فعلتها لويس!
You did it! You did it man!
لقد فعلتها لقد فعلتها يا رجل!
LP: How on earth did we do that?
لويس باف: كيف بحق السماء فعلنا ذلك؟
Man: Against the current! You did it against the current!
رجل: ضد التيار لقد قمت بذلك ضد التيار!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
LP: Thank you very much. Thank you very much.
لويس باف: شكرا جزيلا. شكرا جزيلا لكم.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
Audience: Encore!
الجمهور: مرة اخرى!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LP: I'd just like to end off by just saying this:
اريد فقط ان اختم بقول هذا.
It took me four months again to feel my hands.
تطلب مني اربعة اشهر لكي اشعر بيدي.
But was it worth it? Yes, absolutely it was.
لكن هل كان ذلك يستحق العناء نعم حتما.
There are very, very few people who don't know now
هنالك القلة القليل من الناس اللذين لا يدركون الان
about what is happening in the Arctic.
ما يجري في القطب.
And people ask me, "Lewis, what can we do about climate change?"
و يسالني الناس "لويس ماذا عسانا ان نفعل بخصوص التغير المناخي؟"
And I say to them,
فاقول لهم
I think we need to do three things.
اعتقد ان علينا القيام بثلاث اشياء.
The first thing we need to do is we need to break this problem down
الشيء الاول اللذي علينا فعله هو تجزئة هذه المشكلة
into manageable chunks.
الى قطع يمكن التحكم بها.
You saw during that video all those flags.
ترى في هذا الفيديو كل هذه الاعلام.
Those flags represented the countries
هذه الاعلام تمثل البلدان
from which my team came from.
اللتي اتى منها فريقي.
And equally, when it comes to climate change,
و بالمقابل عندما التغير المناخي،
every single country is going to have to make cuts.
كل بلد عليه ان يقوم بحصته.
Britain, America, Japan,
بريطانيا، امريكا، اليابان،
South Africa, the Congo.
جنوب افريقيا، الكنغو.
All of us together, we're all on the same ship together.
كلنا جميعا على متن نفس المركب.
The second thing we need to do is
الامر الثاني للذي علينا فعله هو
we need to just look back
علينا فقط ان ننظر الى الخلف
at how far we have come
الى اي مدى وصلنا
in such a short period of time.
في هكذا فترة زمنية قصيرة.
I remember, just a few years ago, speaking about climate change,
اتذكر سنوات قليلة فارطة تحدثت عن تغير المناخ،
and people heckling me in the back
و كان الناس في الخلف يزعجونني
and saying it doesn't even exist.
و يقولون هذا لاوجود له.
I've just come back from giving a series of speeches
لقدت عدت للتو من القاء سلسلة من الخطابات
in some of the poorest townships in South Africa
في بعض من افقر المدن في جنوب افريفيا
to young children as young as 10 years old.
على اطفال صغار بعمر عشرة سنوات.
Four or five children sitting behind a desk,
اربعة او خمسة اطفال يجلسون الى طاولة واحدة،
and even in those poorest conditions,
و حتى في هذه الظروف المزرية،
they all have a very, very good grasp
كان لهم جميعا فهم جيد
of climate change.
للتغير المناخي.
We need to believe in ourselves.
نحتاج ان نؤمن بانفسنا.
Now is the time to believe.
الان هو زمن الايمان.
We've come a long way. We're doing good.
لقد مشينا دربا طويلا اننا نقوم بعمل جيد.
But the most important thing we must do
و لكن الشيء الاكثر اهمية اللذي علينا فعله
is, I think, we must all walk to the end of our lives
هو في اعتقادي علينا جميعا ان نمشي الى منتهى حيواتنا
and turn around, and ask ourselves a most fundamental question.
و الالتفات و نسال انفسنا سوالا مهما جدا.
And that is, "What type of world do we want to live in,
و هو "ما طبيعة العالم اللذي نود العيش فيه،
and what decision are we going to make today
و ماهي القرارات التي علينا اتخاذها اليوم
to ensure that we all live
لكي نضمن اننا نعيش
in a sustainable world?"
في عالم مستدام؟
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very, very much.
ايها السيدات و السادة شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)